Clinicians want to make things better.
They really want to solve the problems
that we see in healthcare day in day
out.
We really have to stop the approach that
we've been taking for such a long time,
which is let's build it for them. You
guys are really, really good at solving
really difficult problems. The challenge
that I see is that you're not asking the
people who need these solutions the
most.
But I think there's a reason they're not
asking.
Most pilots are failing.
I've never been a fan of pilots. The
amount of energy and people's time you
have to invest in implementing driving
adoption of a new technology is
enormous. Very recently we wanted to
make some changes [music] now in the way
that we track data from the ambulatory
setting. So if you ask anyone that's a
visionary in healthcare and in
technology, you can't go against it. You
have to leverage those wearable devices
to track the data and then determine how
that data comes into your system. How
you going to analyze it and how you
going to improve care based on that
data? Well, if that goes through layers
and layers and layers of governance and
the first layer being the approval from
the clinical standpoint and that's
taking forever, but you can't govern by
committee everything. At some point,
someone needs to make a decision and
move things forward. Once it goes to
legal, it's there for months.
You might hear the amen corner of the
entire
clinical community. Welcome back to the
Signal Room. I'm Chris Hutchins. Every
week we try to get past the demo and
into the part nobody puts on the slide.
What it actually takes to make AI work
inside a health system and what happens
when it doesn't. My guest today has
lived both sides of that. Angel Mena is
an internal medicine physician who came
up through the floor of primary care
residency program director of training
and next generation of doctors. He's now
chief medical officer at simpler sitting
over the operational backbone of health
care credentiing scheduling workforce
compliance more than a decade at Tri
Health and he helped build one of the
first cloud clinical communication
platforms over at Halo Health. He's got
a line I keep coming back to. You can't
just layer AI on a top of a broken
process. Anhill, welcome to the signal
room.
Thank you very much for having me today
and for that kind introduction.
Well, it's it's my pleasure and you
know, as I looked at your your
background, I mean, it was clear to me
that you've got some things that our our
audience really will be interested in
hearing about. Um, before we dig in,
let me give me a short version of, you
know, who you are, what you do at
Simpler, and maybe a little bit about
your personal story. what what brought
you into the medical profession?
Yeah, that's always a great question to
start and uh the way that I like to
address it is uh in my experience as a
program director and as an educator of
the next generation of physicians, you
interview a lot of people and you get to
meet the the reasons or or learn about
the reasons why people go into medicine
and you end up with um three main
categories. You read review their
personal statements and that includes
myself as well. you've you went into
medicine because you wanted to um you
wanted to to make a difference for your
community or there was a medical reason
personal or family member that convinced
you really wanted to do this or you had
a parent uh that was a doctor. So those
kind of shape the reasons why you go
into medicine uh you want to change the
community and for me it's been a
blessing. My university has been just
being involved in technology and
startups from the beginning. As as a
physician, I feel like I've always been
able to change and make my community
better, one patient at a time. As an
educator, I feel like every patient that
one of my residents touches a patient
that I have the opportunity to improve
their health. In the technology world
now, everything is exponential. when we
introduce some program so some uh
platform that it really facilitates and
reduces friction in healthcare to
deliver better care now I've been able
to touch so many more patients at a time
so my journey started in as I was uh
starting my practice and I was asked to
to consult for this clinical
communication platform and since then
it's been a fantastic journey and
experience in healthcare technology
it's just amazing to me in light of some
of the conversations that I had recently
with folks, you know, the the
unbelievable administrative burden that
that we've been layering on clinicians
over the last couple decades with all of
our quote technology improvements.
Yeah.
Um the the the weight of what you do as
a physician is is it's enough all by
itself to be a full-time job. And I
always see find inspiration when I talk
to somebody like yourself who's got all
these other things you're involved with
whether it's administrative uh executive
administrative oversight responsibility
or you know coaching residents. Um it
may be you know being on a show like
this but then thinking about how much
further you can go in terms of the
mission and your impact to patients that
are actually being seen by someone that
you've trained. Yeah,
but then all this all this technology
stuff AI is not for a hobbyist and
clearly you've you've understood that
you know technology in a whole different
way. So I just want to acknowledge that.
I mean this is it's truly impressive and
I admire uh someone like yourself who
actually can do all of these things and
I'm quite sure that you're you have a
family that you're taking care of as
well which just makes all of this even
more mind-blowing to me. So thank thank
you for what you do. No, I appreciate it
and and I I get that a lot. Um the part
of how do you do this? You know, how can
you have your head in one side and then
on the other side? I I I have this
vision of the near future where a lot of
the things that I do administratively
will be facilitated in a way that I will
be able to focus on the things that
really that really really matter. Right?
That's taking care of the patient. uh
spending time looking at the patient
rather than sitting in front of a
computer. Uh spending more time with my
residents as I coach them and mentor
them into the the profession of
medicine. But it is to date it is very
difficult to navigate the waters of the
administrative side and the clinician
side. Yeah, I think that being being in
the more technical and data side of
healthcare, I I think that there's a
perhaps a level of misunderstanding when
it comes to uh the adoption of this kind
of stuff and you know technical people
get really excited about cool stuff. Uh
but at the end of the day, how many how
many of these things that we've as a
hobbyist develop and try to force on our
our clinical people is actually
supporting the real mission? Is it
actually making things easier for you?
Is it giving you more time with the
patient? These are the things that we've
got to really dial in and we better do
it quickly because AI is moving faster
than than
any industry, but in particular the
challenges in healthcare. It's it's it's
like of the utmost importance that we
get our act together. We do it like
yesterday. Um let's talk about your your
journey a little bit. So you were a
practicing internist.
Yeah.
And a program director training
residents.
What did you see from inside the exam
room in the teaching service that made
you want to see where the operational
decisions are getting made?
The the the main thing was that we want
to participate. I believe clinicians
want to make things better. They really
want to solve the problems that we see
in healthcare day in day out. And our
voice was not there. So you know on one
side I had that desire to help and on
the other side I it's always I was in
the right place at the right time when
someone raised their hand and said hey
we're trying to solve a problem can you
come and and help us out you know and I
said absolutely you know I have the
interest in doing this and that led to
conversations and we develop a clinical
communication platform that was a
problem we needed to solve at the time
where we always talk about fragmentation
and silos in healthcare but Just 12, 13
years ago, we were really broken in
communication. We were we had had no
ways of knowing who was on call, who was
taking care of a patient. You had to
call a a unit and talk to a unit clerk
and then figure out who was the nurse
taking care of the patient, and then who
was on call in a piece of paper that was
completely outdated because things
changed on the go. So we wanted to solve
that problem and I was called into it
and it was just a fantastic experience.
I call it my university in technology
because you go from being called in to
just provide your clinical expertise and
then next thing you know you're sitting
with a UX team and you're sitting with a
marketing team and the product team and
and then and then following that you're
on the road with the sales team trying
to get your product out there to the to
to healthare systems which is very
interesting
because clearly you don't have enough to
do right
yeah [laughter]
I have to say at that time I was
starting in in my clinical practice. So
that provide me a little bit more
flexibility to get into the technology
side as well.
It's amazing and I'm sure you've heard
this and you've been probably advocating
this find this about his sons as well is
we we really have to stop the approach
that we've been taking for such a long
time which is let's build it for them.
We got to build it with them.
Um, one of the things I've told a couple
of like chief innovation officers that
I've worked with over the years, I said,
you know, you guys are really, really
good at solving really difficult
problems. The challenge that I I see is
that you're not asking the people who
need these solutions the most. Uh,
you're doing some cool stuff. I won't
argue that. But if you ask a physician,
I don't care what their EHR platform is,
what are your pain points, they got a
list. I mean, I'm sure that's your
experience, too, right?
Yeah. No, absolutely. I But I think
there's a reason they're not asking.
They they they are acknowledging that
the work that we do is very hard and
that we have to take our time and
dedicate it to our patients. So, for for
on one side, I feel like they're trying
to protect us, but the problems that
we're trying to solve have to come from
who's at the bedside, you know, and not
just the physician, right? it's the
nurse, the resp respiratory therapist,
the physical therapist. So these are the
people that really understand what's
happening at the bedside and how to
solve those problems. So we have to
figure out how to pull them into
conversations to then go and find the
solution, the vendor that's going to
help us.
There's a reality that I'm that I think
people are not cognizant of many times.
I'm sure you've run into this as well.
Uh there's an expectation somehow from
people that are doing like data
analytics for example that an executive
that's running an organization should
have an understanding of the things if
they've spent their entire career maybe
20 years developing the skill sets and
the knowledge of how to do that and
there's just misplaced expectation of
who's responsible to have for them to be
able to understand enough to be making
good decisions and that's one of the
things I've advocated for written about
even recently it's the responsibility of
a chief data officer like me for example
I had to figure out what level of
information could inform the CIO to go
ask for budget for things I might have
to dial it in a little differently to
talk to this the C chief operating
officer who's got less of an
understanding of the technology he just
needs the facts needs to have verifiable
facts needs to be able to trust it so
it's on people that are dealing with
this stuff in the trenches whether it's
development shop just you know could be
your innovation group whatever it is
it's our responsibility to come to you
with the information that you need serve
it up concisely so you get to the point
and you you have what you need to
execute or tell us look you guys are
nuts this isn't going to work
yeah it's it's it's interesting uh in
that journey that I was talking about uh
through the clinical communication
platform startup my former CEO and
founder of the clinical communication
platform he when we would go out on the
road and talk to healthcare systems and
in this commercial enterprise. We
learned really quick that you have to
target what we call uh the three amigos.
And sometimes it would be the three
enemos, which is the opposite of of of
being friendly, which is, you know, you
do need your your um CFO, you need the
COO or CEO, and you need the CMO, and
I'm going to the chief medical officer,
not marketing, because that confusion
happens a lot. uh the the chief medical
officer and and with medical I'm
obviously summarizing everyone that that
is clinical because sometimes it's a
chief um nursing officer but my point
was you needed that combination but the
message was different
you know with the chief medical officer
how are you going to improve the
outcomes of your patient of your
patients how are you going to reduce the
friction and and give more time to your
physicians to your nurses
Right. When you talk to the CFO, you're
going to now bring a conversation about,
you know, the ROI and this it's it's an
enter it's it's an industry that's very
difficult to put a hard ROI on.
Okay. Because some of the outcomes,
they're very difficult to measure. So,
but they're going to hear how do you
build that ROI around the platform? uh
with a chief operational officer, you
obviously how do you facilitate some of
those processes that improve operations.
So that message needed to be tweaked
when you talk to to one or the other.
But at the end of the day, they also
need to come to the table together and
understand how each one of them was
going to support the other. It was an
interesting learning curve for us.
Yeah. I mean, the CFO conversations are
the the really challenging ones to to
really frame because the kinds of things
that you were talking about, they're
actually reducing risk, reducing
readmission rates, uh reducing uh costs,
but things that are not actually on the
P&L.
Exactly.
You can tell me you're going to reduce
the length of stay, but I have to budget
the way actually things are flowing
today. And it's a really hard hurdle to
clear particularly when you're dealing
with like a hospital chart condition for
example.
Yeah.
You know they'll give you the credit for
the last day which means the the very
lowest uh cost day that you're leaving
they'll allow you credit for that if
you've done something to influence it.
Yeah. There's a big yeah there's a big
chance that we won't
the cost actually explodes as soon as
that acquired that condition occurs and
then it goes flat for extended period of
time massive massive cost that does not
fit the model that they actually like to
use which is just the normal admission
you know they come in they're sick they
have a procedure few days later they're
gone no complications that's what they
model that's what they'll model for you
yeah it's it's that and that is the
conversation vision. Um it's very
difficult to for the most part to impact
that top line, you know, uh then but
then you're making your argument how
could we improve your bottom line, you
know, by cost savings and by other other
ways of then the delivering the outcome
and the value that we're offering.
Well, I I think I I would probably want
to advocate for the the one measure that
I'm pretty sure you would want to do is
look at look, we are reducing mortality.
This is not a calculation. you want to
meet the people we saved, we can do
that. It's it's so it's a quality of
care. It's an outcomes. It's a
conversation and for gosh sakes, it's a
PR boost if you're h getting a
reputation like that. So, this is an a
conversation and I love you, you kind of
leaned into this a little bit because
this is the kind of conversation that
should be happening uh within
organizations and you know when you have
a chance to educate a board for example,
yeah,
that's a great opportunity you shouldn't
miss. And similarly with your CFOs, most
of them are very passionate they've ever
worked with.
Mhm.
But you really have to figure out how
what's their language so that they can
actually get, you know, get what you're
saying and figure out how far they can
trust and that trust piece of it when
you don't have a guaranteed bottom line
number you can give them. That's where
it's a bit tricky.
Yeah. I mean, at the end of the day, I
mean, you you you want to show that
you're
you're delivering better care. How you
measure the better care, right, is if
you hit the mortality, if you hit
different metrics and you're delivering
better care by uh while engaging more
with your team members, with your staff,
with your employees, right? That that's
that's kind of the goal here and what
the board, you know, and your executive
leadership want to hear. Uh how do you
go about that? How do you do that? what
what are the processes and and the
technology and the people that you're
putting in place to also make sure is
sustainable and that you can scale. Uh
because what we're seeing is a lot of
that how how do how do we increase
access in healthcare and to increase
access you have to you know either you
acquire merge or you implement some new
technology but all of them all of that
needs to be scalable. So, let's get into
maybe a a bit of a a sensitive area for
Okay.
a lot of people. Um, so
a lot of the conversations around AI,
they're really chasing the clinical
demo.
You work in the the unglamorous layer,
credentiing, scheduling, compliance,
contracts, super fun, exciting stuff for
people, I'm sure. Where is AI genuinely
delivering right now in production? Not
really in a pilot. I mean, it's it's
getting real results.
I would say that operationally, I mean,
you you did framework in quality and
safety and contracts. I would definitely
believe in in the contracting world,
we're able to summarize and redline
things way faster than we used to and
get that process moving forward. But
that's I think you know table stakes
when it comes to AI in contracting
quality and safety is uh same thing
right now we're summarizing
understanding u timelines
um when are things due when when things
are uh um need to be submitted so that
we can move from move along the
credentiing process in scheduling for
example is another area that we could um
[snorts] uh leverage AI to anticipate
staffing needs uh and also understand
what competencies are needed are
required for specific staffing clinical
practice you know and and I'm going a
little bit beyond because I feel that
clinical practice is where we've seen
most of the AI really show it not like a
demo AI but really show it in imaging so
stroke diagnosis uh coronary disease
diagnosis something that's very strong
where AI is helping us um and definitely
you know documentation
We're seeing a lot of strength of AI
practically being applied for
documentation.
So here here's a a bit of a challenging
one.
Okay.
We hear that most pilots are failing.
Mhm.
Let's let's talk a little bit about what
actually makes them fail or or stall.
You said
you can't layer AI onto a broken
process, but most systems can't fix
those processes fast enough. So, are we
about to spend five years making broken
processes run faster and calling it
transformation?
Think about I I this is my personal
opinion. I've never been a fan of
pilots. All right? Because if you think
about it, the amount of energy uh and
people's time you have to invest in
implementing driving adoption uh of a
new technology is is enormous. How do
you do that for a smaller opportunity
when you're really trying to show a
value of a new technology? So, is the
commitment really there to drive the
engagement so that you can show the
value of the platform? And I think that
is my biggest challenge with pilots. I I
believe that it is extremely important
uh from the customer side to partner
with a vendor that after the appropriate
vetting process and going through the
appropriate governance process, you feel
that they're going to be your partner
and you got you're going to start at a
point and then you might need to develop
more throughout the cycle so that you
can achieve what you were looking for.
So I in my opinion that's the challenge
with pilots of any technology. Now when
it comes to AI now take that how what's
the life not the life cycle but what's a
technology cycle of of of AI nowadays by
the time you finish a pilot you're
probably moving on to the next thing
because that's that's changing. So you
have to understand that things are just
pretty they're moving pretty fast
nowadays.
Yeah. I I think the the the stuff that
people are starting to realize cuz
they're getting they're running into
some bumps in the road is that you know
this is not a typical development cycle
evolution. It just isn't. The speed that
you mentioned it's really really rapid
and by the time you realize that you've
actually veered off cuz things drift for
a variety of reasons. You may be at a
point where you've really got off the
really on the off the reservation
because you think you've got a you
figure figured it out because you
realize, oh, we put some bad data in the
air. Let's go. Let's get rid of the
data. You've trained the model already.
This is one of the issues that people
have to start to understand.
When you sign off on governance for an
AI model, you need a game plan with
continuity to keep that thing from going
off the rails. I mean, that's the that's
the challenge I think. And I think that
kind of brings me to uh really a
leadership concern. How does a leader
tell real improvement from expensive
automation of dysfunction? I mean, they
may not even be aware of some of the
things that are under the hood.
That that's that's a great question and
and I don't know if there's there's a a
great answer to it because in fact, I've
been having conversations with with some
groups that that's what they're trying
to define. how how do we call this
success, you know, and and it's
sometimes it's very difficult just to
put a metric that's already been uh
leveraged in healthcare to to talk about
success, but you need more data. You
need to understand how it's implemented,
how it's adopted, how it's driving
change, how it's replacing uh processes
that were standardized and that were
working, but now they're shorting the
time of that process. I I don't believe
we have the right answer for that. But
as we go through some more of this
implementations,
I feel like we're going to start
defining success in in the AI world and
healthcare.
What kind of leads into the the sign off
question? What has to be settled first
before someone signs off on what has to
be true underneath?
Well, first of all, I would uh add that
we need we need to define ownership. we
see in healthcare many times is um I'm a
physician I raise my hand and I feel
like I need this AI technology or this
group of physicians okay and then we
take it through the current governance
structure but because it's technology it
falls under it but as we decide if we
were discussing about how do we choose
technology and some and how there's a
failure of bringing the right subject
matter experts into the conversation
when it comes to ownership
implementation and adoption it's the
same conversation. You know, as an IT
expert or is expert, I'm not going to be
the one who's going to drive the
adoption. So, I need you to partner with
me in delivering this. So, I would
always say ownership and and is is
extremely important. Make sure that you
outline what is the defined success,
whatever that is, you know, define
success. And then how do you sign off?
The one thing that still scares me in
this world of AI and multiple vendors is
security. Uh you can't you can't sign
off on new technology. You can't have uh
you can't have the the shadow IT uh in
healthcare which is a huge problem.
You know you need to take every
technology through the same process of
vetting the security side because we
know that what a risk that is.
It's an interesting thing to try to deal
with this ownership. There's so many
angles with it. This kind of talks about
um getting into some terminology that
people have kind of tossed around. It's
been academic for years.
Uh but when you we talk about process
data process ownership governance,
what's the thing that teams skip that
keeps coming back to bite them?
Well, I and not specifically about data
but uh just the governance processes in
general. I feel like that um it just
creates the framework to advance. Okay.
But sometimes I feel it can slow down
innovation. And let me make my point. Uh
so many times when we raise our hands in
the clinical world and we want to drive
innovation, we we get ourselves in front
of this governance uh pathway that it um
again slows down the the process. And
unless you have a very tight system in
place, you're going to have
disengagement from that clinician at the
beginning that really wanted to drive
change. So you have to have a very
strong governance structure that is got
tight processes and and you have there
has to have some vision
and and I'll give you an example. Um
very recently we wanted to make some
changes now uh in in in the way that we
track data from the ambulatory setting.
So from devices, you know, your wearable
devices, if you ask anyone that's a
visionary in healthcare and in
technology, you can't go against it. you
you have to leverage those wearable
devices to track the data and then
determine how that data comes into your
system. How you going to analyze it and
how you going to improve care based on
that data? Well, if that goes through
layers and layers and layers of
governance and and and the first layer
being the approval from the clinical
standpoint and that's taking forever,
you're going to disengage with the
people that that really want to drive
innovation if that makes sense. Yeah. in
in that case and I've seen this before
too. It's like if the academic exercise
is what people are feeling the way that
the governance has been been approached
in the organization the next thing you
know you've got two and three levels
down from the person who really owns it
which kind of leads into the big
question for me in your experience.
Yeah.
Who needs to be in the room to make
these kind of conversations effective to
where you get to conclusions and you get
to policies that are that are going to
be carried out? Yeah, definitely needs
to be multi-isiplinary, multi-dep
departmental, but the initial in the
initial um idea or innovation needs to
be vetted at the clinical role. So it's
it's a clinical role call it you know
what you wish chief clinical officer
chief uh CMIO CIO or a group of them
that are vetting this idea with the
right vision saying yes let's move it
forward now you're starting to size and
price and cost this whole idea from the
from the IT is group from compliance
from risk from executive
So now you have to go through that
process. But the clinical stamp you
received.
Now let's size this. Now whether it
falls in your road map at the top of
your priority list or the bottom of your
priority list, it's going to depend on
many variables. But clinically stamp it,
move forward. We can't just slow down on
the clinical side.
Right. You know, I I totally agree with
you and that that's one of the things
that I've taken seriously is I've worked
with organizations just being in a chief
data officer kind of role is there's a
lot of people who are going to throw up
the caution flags and I love that they
do that. I don't need to do that. Well,
I have to find those things that we can
say yes to that are actually going to
make a difference and start to relieve
the burden and the pressure that takes
you away from what you went into
medicine for. to to help people uh not
to work in the EHRs and and key things
while the patients probably annoyed
because they're not getting the facetime
that they used to get before we improved
everything with technology.
Absolutely. And and I'm a believer of
processes. I'm a believer in the
multid-disiplinary approach of groups
and committees.
But you can't govern by committee
everything. At some point, someone needs
to make a decision and move things
forward.
Yes.
So, and that's why I feel like it
happens a lot in healthcare and you know
sometimes I'm I'm guilty of that as
well. But it's just about let's make the
decision and move forward people. Things
are moving very fast and we need some
help.
If you listen carefully I think you
might hear the amen corner of the entire
clinical community. [laughter]
Oh, so you you you've kind of framed
this very nicely. So let's talk about
shared governance. What it looks like
when clinicians, IT, operations all have
a stake and maybe they don't all want
the same thing. Oh, and by the way, the
risk management, the legal teams,
compliance teams, the CESOs, all of them
are very, very busy and they may not
want this to be a big part of what
they're doing. However, they really do
need to be at the table.
Yeah, I believe there's multiple
permutations of what that group looks
like. you've outlined probably the the
right groups that need to be involved in
conversations. I have to go back to you
know if this is a clinical process you
have to have a one clinical two clinical
group that is moving forward things uh
from the clinical standpoint just from
the clinical standpoint you know and
then if you figure out how to get the
legal side to get their processes you
know moving faster let me know because
that's something that we are always
looking for you know what they say once
it goes to legal it's there for months.
Yeah. Well, you know, I I I'll just tell
you hopefully this will feel good to
you.
Yeah.
Uh my most recent experience when I was
working with a health system,
I found it amazing that some of the
people that historically from a role
standpoint
would be the ones that they didn't even
want to talk about it because it was too
complicated, it was too risky, they
didn't want to be contributing to a
decision that like had downside to it.
But the organization I was at, uh, there
were more than one of of the legal team
that were enthusiastic and when we
brought something to be considered, they
were really really aggressive to go
through it and they knew what the stakes
were and so they were processing things
very very quickly, giving us the things
that they we needed to pay attention to,
but they were helping accelerate, not
slow it down. Same with the seesaw and
the risk and compliance people. So that
there are people in most organizations
probably but at the same time a lot of
these people are also uh carrying a
pretty significant workload because
health careers in the provider sector
tends to be overstretched for a variety
of reasons and probably the more
significant one is that we have
regulatory bodies that are essentially
trying to figure out how they can
reimburse us less for for what we're
doing in the provider space. But let's
talk about the the human side now. Buro
is running through everything at this
point on the clinical care side. Um,
from from your career and I'm sure they,
you know, you've had to figure out how
do you balance this and how do you how
do you manage it yourself with everyone
now selling AI as the cure for burnout?
Have you seen it quietly make burnout
worse? What is what does adoption look
like, you know, from the floor, not from
the slide deck?
That's that's an interesting question.
So I recently have a had a conversation
with a couple of primary care physicians
who've been practicing primary care for
about 30 years and they went through the
changes in documentation paper charts
then introduction of the EMR then the
next thing and obviously now they're in
the AI revolution and they would say I I
see a lot of patients you know I am
exhausted at the end of a day you know I
spend a lot of time of communicating
back and forth forth with everyone that
needs to take care of my patient and my
patients, I don't want to introduce
another technology. I figure out my
process. You know, as much as I'm going
to complain, you know, if if I introduce
something else, it's it's going to
disrupt my day. So, there's there's
still opportunities that we have in the
clinical workflow world where I I don't
know if we're going to solve their
problems. Okay. I think we need to, you
know, they've already figured out their
processes. it's okay and we just have to
acknowledge that. Now for the other
group of physicians, it is working very
well. So, uh tools like uh ambiencece AI
for example, and you've probably heard
about this where documentation has been
facilitated tremendously that need some
tweaking, need some adjustment. There's
still some hallucination. We we need to
be on top of it, but that's just going
to get better. It's worked tremendously
in reducing what we call the pajama
time, which is basically documentation
and EMR time after your regular hours.
Also, when we're when we're um with the
patient in the patient's in the in the
office, we have time to look at the
patient. You're not just documenting at
the same time. You're really taking your
time to look at the patient, have
conversation, listen, do a good physical
exam. That those things were very
difficult with 15 minutes.
I'm glad you you you mentioned this. I
think we've gotten some things really
goofed up. So, we wanted to make things
more efficient, but the main objective
was improved billing. We did away with
the transcriptionist
and we decided, okay, well, the doctor
can do the documentation.
I think we replaced the wrong function,
but you know, here we are trying to dig
out of that now.
I agree. I think we were so focused on
what we spent the most time on on a
daily on a day-to-day to fix that
problem that we tried to put the AI
around that instead of understanding why
how did we end up spending so much time
in the EMR and you start thinking well
it was because of all the regulatory all
the building and coding all the this
other stuff
that creat created you you bloated your
documentation. I asked myself if we
would have gone first for those things
with AI. Could that have solved our
documentation challenges? Because we've
always been documenting before and after
EMR. We've always been documenting and I
think we still want to do it. I I
believe we still want to be the ones um
expressing our thoughts, our clinical uh
assessments and our plans. You know,
whether now you can have an AI tool that
takes what I am verbalizing and create
it into the regulatory components that
that will satisfy uh the requirements
and then you're done. Um so I I think I
wonder if there's going to be a flip on
on how we'd leverage AI in the clinical
arena for for documentation billing and
code.
Yeah, to me that's a natural evolution.
And I I hope that people are working on
it already. But if you can actually get
accurate documentation using that
technology that it naturally lends
itself to coding workflows where you're
not going to need a whole bunch of
coders if you've got really clean
documentation record because the the the
coding piece of it is entirely
rules-based. So, you know, I know that
people have got some great stuff in in
that space that's doing extraordinarily
well and it's outperforming humans,
which is great. But that bridge I think
could be a really big differentiator and
I'm hoping that we start to see some of
that coming out at a scale pretty soon
because it's definitely needed.
Yes.
Um so a CMO or CMIO is about to sign off
on a big implementation this quarter.
One thing what do they settle before
they sign and where can you f where can
people find you?
Where do [gasps]
um so so let me let me clarify. Am I the
do I have the vendor hat or do I have
the customer hat?
Well, I what I'm what I'm getting at is,
you know, I I just want to get that, you
know, get your to weigh in on what is
the main the biggest thing that they
should understand before they sign. The
second piece of it is really more how
can people, you know, re get in touch
with you um through your expertise and
and your guidance. So I think the
conversation has clearly hit some things
that I am sure there's a lot of
listeners are going to want to have a
conversation in because I think you've
you've got a lot to say in in a lot of
different uh arenas that are everyone's
working in and probably struggling with
you need to get from the CMIO from the
hospital the healthcare system
standpoint you really need to to have
someone has to have ownership because I
need to build a relationship with that
group that person that group or that
role This is going to be a journey where
there's things that you're going to ask
me to do that I want to sit down and
understand what are your needs, what are
the problems that you want to solve so
that we can develop it together.
Especially when you're talking about
talking about uh not necessarily point
solutions but at the platform level you
know you touch so many groups so many
departments so many variables that you
really want to make sure you have the
right people who are connected in a
quarterly basis making sure we're doing
business reviews what how do we define
the next goals the next success and we
come back and review the reality is that
this is where the analogy is in the
healthcare industry this is an ongoing
quality and improvement project with a
specific process and methodology where
you have to plan, you have to do, you
have to review, you have to be nimble
and adapt to the changes that are
coming.
Yeah. Nimble and and adapting. I don't
think we're often accused of that
healthcare. U it's unfortunate. Um but
the you mentioned the regulatory stuff.
I mean, there's so much pressure coming
from every direction and these these
arbitrary uh regulatory mandates come
out from time to time. They give you a
target, you get to the 11th hour, you've
spent a ton of money getting ready and
then they oh, they're not ready.
Yeah. Incredibly frustrating.
And and I and going back to your point
that I want to clarify when we're
talking about the governance and you
know, the legal team and and and and
risk and compliance. Uh I do agree with
you. There's a culture shift. People now
understand that we need to move at a
different pace and at all levels. And
when we talk about administrative burden
for clinicians, well, those same
administrative burdens exist in all
those other groups. And they're also
trying to figure out how to implement
their own technologies to keep processes
moving forward. So once we get that
culture shift of we need to move
forward, we need to adopt, we need to
show success from all layers, all levels
of of the healthcare industry. I think
that's when we're going to find that
that the right formula.
Yeah. I think as we as we wrap up, I
think there's something that you you've
kind of highlighted here and it's when
you're dealing with all of these these
different functions and you know it's
cliche, but if everyone owns it, no one
owns it.
No. Oh, right. So, in that ownership
conversation, one of the things that you
know if I'm seeing a lot of bumps here
because if you are in a let's say you're
in operations
and I'm in I'm in the clinical space, I
have a good sense of what kind of
information I can actually put into a
model without exposing anything
revealing from a HIPPA standpoint.
Mhm.
And independently the operations people
they have the same kind of a sense and
they're very comfortable that they're
not going to put the wrong things out
there. But the gap that exists is the p
is the piece that neither is responsible
for it and there's risk there because if
and I'm sure you've seen this happen
inadvertently now with geni it's very
likely to happen that it's actually
going to try to find a bridge for that
and if it finds that bridge then
everything becomes exposed and and it
introduces risk. So love you just kind
of weigh in on how you think the best
way is to start to put some really
formal structure around that. Um some
organizations are you know bringing in a
uh a chief AI officer some maybe even
fractional whatever but whatever that
role is whatever we want to call it I
mean I think that's something that we
should pay attention to and I don't
think that's the biggest cost. What are
your thoughts on it?
That's a great question. So every year
we actually release a survey. We call
the compass survey because we really
want to make sure we're aligned with the
direction of the industry. And the focus
is to get the the insight from the
clinical group and leadership, the
technology technologies leadership and
the operational leadership. And it's
getting better year-over-year.
But when we started doing it about 3
four years ago, the descent in the
objectives and goals of a fiscal year
from each one of those group was more
than 50%. Obviously technology group was
focusing in technology, you know, and
and we started hearing a lot about
security. The clinical group was into
burnout and delivering care and we saw a
lot of the operational side focus on
supply chain. Obviously, we saw a lot of
the supply chain issues and and and then
and then staffing, right? Staffing was a
big problem.
We we've we've always felt that those
were the three groups that we needed to
target, you know, to make sure that
we're aligning. But with AI, as you
mentioned, what is that connection, that
bridge between one and the other? Who
who's going to show what is that gap? Is
AI going to do it? You know, do we need
do we need a human? I I believe AI is
going to help us connect better and and
find find the bridges between one group
and the other especi especially clinical
and and operational. Now I feel they're
more connected and that's what our
survey says. The framework is still
going to be to look back at your
processes and make sure that you have
the right process in place. Leverage AI
to find those processes before you you
institute technology that's going to
build those bridges. It's a tough
question. I will I will give you that. I
mean, huh? [laughter] It's a tough
question to answer.
I I I I just one of the things that I've
experienced myself, and I'm sure you've
you've found some of these things, too,
where I've been working in an AI model,
just building some efficiency for
myself.
Yeah.
And, you know, I'll notice I I'll ask it
if it can do something and then all of a
sudden it's gone and connected to other
pieces of my model that I didn't
authorize it to and I never intended it
to. But it just it's it's about solving
the problem. And it assumes if I'm
asking that that I want I want them to
do it. So the the the big takeaway for
me in that space is really around you if
you're going to have people using the
technology they have to be trained at
how to prompt it because if you don't do
that these things are going to happen
and it's even in administrative area it
can go off the rails and it's it's
really really hard to hit the reset
button once these things have been
trained. they're going to remember it
whether you want them to or not which is
a really significant problem.
Yeah. And for the most part for us
that's being involved in Gen AI tools.
You know when you're talking about
Agentic AI and then you have a Gent that
lives in operations and clinical and
this they're generating their own
connections. that's generating their own
uh problem solving capabilities and we
want to make sure there is there is some
guart rails around that that we humans
are monitoring what's happening in the
background.
No, I could could not have said that
better. Well, for my listeners, I just
want to let you know that when the
episode be up, there's going to be some
show notes there. uh gave you all kinds
of information and ways to get in touch
with uh with Anhill and probably some
some good reference material as well. So
I want to make sure that that you you
all can really benefit from you know his
his expertise and uh Anel I can't thank
you enough for being on the show as
always I've learned a whole bunch of
things from you and you know it it's
been a absolute pleasure thank you so
much for coming on the show. No, I
appreciate the time, the questions, the
conversation, and I've learned a lot
also from this conversation today. Thank
you very much.
That's it for this episode of the Signar
Room. If today's conversation sparked
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming